Autofire Plugin

Introduction

The autofire plugin allows you to simulate repeatedly pressing an emulated button by holding down a key or button combination. This can help people with certain disabilities or injuries play shooting games, and may help reduce the risk of repetitive strain injuries (or keyboard damage).

To configure the autofire plugin, activate the main menu (press Tab during emulation by default), select Plugin Options, and then select Autofire. Configured autofire buttons for the current system are listed, along with their repetition rates and activation hotkeys (initially there will be no autofire buttons configured). Select an autofire button to change settings, or choose Add autofire button to set up a new autofire button. See Autofire buttons settings for details on setting up an autofire button. You can delete an autofire button by highlighting it in the menu and pressing the UI Clear key (Del/Delete/Forward Delete on the keyboard by default).

Autofire settings are saved in the autofire folder in the plugin data folder (see the homepath option). A file is created for each system with autofire buttons configured, named according to the system’s short name (or ROM set name), with the extension .cfg. For example, autofire settings for Super-X will be saved in the file superx.cfg in the autofire folder in your plugin data folder. The autofire settings are stored in JSON format.

Autofire buttons settings

The options for adding a new autofire button or modifying an existing autofire button are the same.

Select Input to set the emulated button that you want to simulate pressing repeatedly. Only digital inputs are supported. Typically you’ll set this to the primary fire button for shooting games. This is most often P1 Button 1 or the equivalent for another player, but it might have a different name. On Konami’s Gradius games, P1 Button 2 is the primary fire button.

Select Hotkey to set the control (or combination of controls) you’ll use to activate the autofire button. This can be any combination that MAME supports for activating a digital input.

On frames and Off frames are the number of consecutive emulated video frames that the emulated button will be held and released for, respectively. Adjust the value with the UI Left/Right keys, or click the arrows. Press the UI Clear key to reset the values to one frame. Lower values correspond to pressing the button at a faster rate. Depending on how fast the system reads inputs, you may need higher numbers than 1 for the system to recognise the button being released and pressed again (e.g. 2 on frames and 2 off frames works for Alcon). Experiment with different values to get the best effect.

When adding a new autofire button, there is a Cancel option that changes to Create after you set the input and hotkey. Select Create to finish creating the autofire button and return to the list of autofire buttons. The new autofire button will be added at the end of the list. Press the UI Back key (Escape/Esc on the keyboard by default), or select Cancel before setting the input/hotkey, to return to the previous menu without creating the new autofire button.

When modifying an existing autofire button, select Done or press the UI Cancel key to return to the list of autofire buttons. Changes take effect immediately.

When modifying an existing autofire button, select Delete to delete the autofire button. The autofire button will be deleted immediately when you select Delete without requiring additional confirmation. You can also delete an autofire button by highlighting it in the list of autofire buttons and pressing the UI Clear key (Del/Delete/Forward Delete on the keyboard by default).

Notes and potential pitfalls

Autofire buttons act as if they’re wired in parallel with MAME’s regular controls. This means that if you set the activation hotkey for an autofire button to a button or key that’s also assigned to one of the emulated inputs directly, you may get unexpected results. Using Gradius as an example:

Suppose you set button 1 on your controller to fire, and set an autofire hotkey to button 1 as well. Holding the button down to shoot will not trigger the autofire effect: the button will never be released as you’re holding the non-autofire button 1 down. This will also happen if you set a different button as autofire (say, button 3 in this case), and hold button 1 down while also pressing button 3.

If you set button 3 on your controller to autofire and assign button 3 to powerup as well, you will trigger the powerup action every time you grab a powerup because the powerup button is also being held down along with the autofire button.

It is recommended that you choose control combinations for autofire hotkeys that are not assigned to any other emulated inputs in the system.

Autofire is not necessarily desirable in all situations. For example using autofire in Super-X with the blue “lightning” weapon equipped at high power levels will only produce a single beam, greatly reducing the weapon’s effectiveness. The fire button must be held down to produce all beams. Some shooting games (e.g. Raiden Fighters) require the primary fire button to be held down for a charged special attack. This means it’s often necessary to have a non-autofire input for the primary fire button assigned to play effectively.

Data Plugin

The data plugin loads information from various external support files so it can be displayed in MAME. If the plugin is enabled, info is show in the Infos tab of the right-hand pane on the system and software selection menus. The info viewer can be shown by clicking the toolbar button on the system and software selection menus, or by choosing External DAT View from the main menu during emulation (this menu item will not appear if the data plugin is not enabled, or if no information is available for the emulated system).

To set the folders where the data plugin looks for supported files, choose Configure Options on the system selection menu, then choose Configure Directories, and then choose DATs. You can also set the historypath option in your ui.ini file.

Loading large data files like history.xml can take quite a while, so please be patient the first time you start MAME after updating or adding new data files.

The following files are supported:

history.xml

From Gaming-History (formerly Arcade-History)

mameinfo.dat

From MASH’s MAMEINFO [https://mameinfo.mameworld.info/]

messinfo.dat

From progetto-SNAPS MESSINFO.dat [https://www.progettosnaps.net/messinfo/]

gameinit.dat

From progetto-SNAPS GameInit.dat [https://www.progettosnaps.net/gameinit/]

command.dat

from progetto-SNAPS Command.dat [https://www.progettosnaps.net/command/]

score3.htm

Top Scores [http://replay.marpirc.net/txt/scores3.htm] from the MAME Action Replay Page [http://replay.marpirc.net/]

Japanese mameinfo.dat and command.dat

From MAME E2J [https://e2j.net/downloads/]

sysinfo.dat

From the defunct Progetto EMMA site

story.dat

From the defunct MAMESCORE site

If you install hi2txt [https://greatstoneex.github.io/hi2txt-doc/], the data plugin can also show high scores from non-volatile memory or saved by the hiscore support plugin for supported games.

Note that you can only use a single file of each type at a time. You cannot, for example, use the English and Japanese mameinfo.dat files simultaneously.

The data plugin creates a history.db file in the data folder in the plugin data folder (see the homepath option). This file stores the information from the support files in a format suitable for rapid loading. It uses the SQLite3 database format.

Hiscore Support Plugin

The hiscore support plugin saves and restores high scores for games that did not originally save high scores in non-volatile memory. Note that this plugin modifies the contents of memory directly with no coordination with the emulated software, and hence changes behaviour. This may have undesirable effects, including broken gameplay or causing the emulated software to crash.

The plugin includes a hiscore.dat file that contains the information on how to save and restore high scores for supported systems. This file must be kept up-to-date when system definitions change in MAME.

High scores can be saved automatically either on exit, or a few seconds after they’re updated in memory. To change the setting, activate the main menu (press Tab during emulation by default), select Plugin Options, and then select Hiscore Support. Change the Save scores option by highlighting it and using the UI Left/Right keys, or clicking the arrows.

High score data is saved in the hiscore folder in the plugin data folder (see the homepath option). A file with a name corresponding the system short name (or ROM set name) with the extension .hi. For example, high scores for the game Moon Cresta will be saved in the file mooncrst.hi in the hiscore folder in your plugin data folder. The settings for the hiscore support plugin are stored in the file plugin.cfg in the hiscore folder in the plugin data folder (this file is in JSON format).

Input Macro Plugin

Introduction

The input macro plugin allows you to trigger a sequence of emulated input actions with a key or button combination. This can help people with disabilities or injuries that make some input sequences difficult. It can also be used as a way to cheat in games that require rapid sequences of inputs, like the running events in Track & Field, or the eating minigame in Daisu-Kiss.

To configure the input macro plugin, activate the main menu (press Tab during emulation by default), select Plugin Options, and then select Input Macros. Configured input macros for the current system are listed, along with their activation sequences (initially there will be no input macros configured). Select a macro to edit it, or choose Add macro to set up a new input macro. See Editing input macros for details on editing input macros. You can delete an input macro by highlighting it in the menu and pressing the UI Clear key (Del/Delete/Forward Delete on the keyboard by default). You can also delete a macro by selecting the macro to edit it and then selecting Delete macro from the menu.

Input macros are saved in the inputmacro folder in the plugin data folder (see the homepath option). A file is created for each system with input macros configured, named according to the system’s short name (or ROM set name), with the extension .cfg. For example, input macros for Daisu-Kiss will be saved in the file daiskiss.cfg in the inputmacro folder in your plugin data folder. The input macros are stored in JSON format.

Editing input macros

The options for editing input macros are the same whether you’re creating a new macro or editing an existing macro. Input macros consist of a sequence of steps. Each step optionally waits for a configurable delay, then activates one or more emulated inputs for a specified duration. You can choose what should happen if the activation sequence is still held when the final step of the macro completes: the emulated inputs can be released, the final step can be prolonged, or the macro can loop back to any step in the sequence.

The settings in first section of the macro editing menu apply to the macro as a whole:

The Name will be used in the list of input macros, so it helps to make it descriptive. Press the UI Select key (Return/Enter on the keyboard or the first button on the first joystick by default) to edit the current name, or press the UI Clear key to type a new name. Press the UI Select key before moving to another menu item to save the new name; press the UI Back key (Escape/Esc on the keyboard by default) to change discard the new name.

Select Activation combination to set the control (or combination of controls) you want to use to activate the macro. Keep in mind that regular input assignments still apply, so you will probably want to use a combination that isn’t being used for any other emulated input in the system.

Set On release to specify what should happen if the activation sequence is released before the macro completes. When set to Stop immediately, any emulated inputs activated by the macro will be released immediately, and no further steps will be processed; when set to Complete macro, the macro will continue to be processed until the end of the final step.

Set When held to specify what should happen if the activation sequence is held after the final step of the macro completes. When set to Release, any inputs activated by the macro will be released, and the macro will not be reactivated until the activation sequence is released and pressed again; when set to Prolong step <n> where <n> is the number of the final step of the macro, the emulated inputs activated by the final step of the macro will remain active until the activation sequence is released; when set to Loop to step <n> where <n> is a step number, macro processing will return to that step, including its delay, if the activation sequence is held after the final step completes.

Each step has delay, duration and input settings:

Set the Delay to the number of emulated video frame intervals to wait before activating the inputs for the step. During the delay, no emulated inputs will be activated by the macro. You can reset the setting to zero by pressing the UI Clear key.

Set the Duration to the number of emulated video frame intervals to hold the emulated inputs for the step active before moving to the next step (or completing the macro in the case of the final step). You can reset the setting to one frame by pressing the UI Clear key.

Set the Input settings to the emulated inputs to activate for the step. Only non-toggle digital inputs are supported. Select Add input to set multiple inputs for a step (this option will only appear after you set the first input for the initially created step when creating a new macro). If the step has multiple inputs, you can highlight an input on the menu and press the UI Clear key to delete it (all steps must have at least one input, so you can’t delete the only input for a step).

If the macro has multiple steps, you can select Delete step to delete a step (this options does not appear if the macro only has a single step). Remember to check that the On release and When held settings are correct after deleting steps.

To add a step to the macro, highlight Add step at position (below the existing steps), use the UI Left/Right keys or click the arrows to set the position where you’d like to insert the new step, and then press the UI Select key (or double-click the menu item) to add the new step. You will be prompted to set the first input for the new step. Remember to check the On release and When held settings after adding steps. The Add step at position item will only appear after you set the first input for the initially created step when creating a new macro.

When creating a new macro, there is a Cancel option that changes to Create after you set the activating sequence and the first input for the initially created step. Select Create to finish creating the macro and return to the list of input macros. The new macro will be added at the end of the list. Press the UI Back key, or select Cancel before setting the activation sequence/input, to return to the previous menu without creating the new macro.

When editing an existing macro, select Done or press the UI Back key to return to the list of input macros. Changes take effect immediately.

When editing an existing macro, select Delete macro to delete the macro. The macro will be deleted immediately when you select Delete macro without requiring additional confirmation. You can also delete a macro by highlighting it in the list of macros and pressing the UI Clear key (Del/Delete/Forward Delete on the keyboard by default).

Example macros

Raiden autofire

This provides player 1 autofire functionality using the space bar. The same thing could be achieved using the Autofire Plugin, but this demonstrates a simple looping macro:

Name: P1 Autofire

Activation combination: Kbd Space

On release: Stop immediately

When held: Loop to step 2

Step 1:

Delay (frames): 0

Duration (frames): 2

Input 1: P1 Button 1

Step 2:

Delay (frames): 4

Duration (frames): 2

Input 1: P1 Button 1

The first step has no delay so that firing begins as soon as the space bar is pressed. The second step has sufficient delay to ensure the game recognises the button being pressed and released again. The second step is repeated as long as the space bar is held down.

Track & Field sprint cheat

This allows you to run in Konami Track & Field by holding a single button. This takes most of the skill (and fun) out of the game:

Name: P1 Sprint

Activation combination: Kbd Shift

On release: Stop immediately

When held: Loop to step 2

Step 1:

Delay (frames): 0

Duration (frames): 1

Input 1: P1 Button 1

Step 2:

Delay (frames): 1

Duration (frames): 1

Input 1: P1 Button 3

Step 3:

Delay (frames): 1

Duration (frames): 1

Input 1: P1 Button 1

This macro rapidly alternates pressing buttons 1 and 3 – the pattern required to run in the game.

Street Fighter II Shoryuken

This macro allows you to perform a right-facing Shōryūken (Dragon Punch) by pressing a single key:

Name: 1P Shoryuken LP

Activation combination: Kbd M

On release: Complete macro

When held: Prolong step 6

Step 1:

Delay (frames): 0

Duration (frames): 1

Input 1: P1 Right

Step 2:

Delay (frames): 1

Duration (frames): 1

Input 1: P1 Down

Step 3:

Delay (frames): 0

Duration (frames): 1

Input 1: P1 Down

Input 2: P1 Right

Step 4:

Delay (frames): 0

Duration (frames): 1

Input 1: P1 Right

Step 5:

Delay (frames): 0

Duration (frames): 1

Input 1: P1 Right

Input 2: P1 Jab Punch

Step 6:

Delay (frames): 0

Duration (frames): 1

Input 1: P1 Jab Punch

This macro involves steps that activate multiple inputs. The macro will complete if the activation sequence is released early, allowing you to tap the key momentarily to perform the move. Holding the activation sequence holds down the attack button.

Plugins

Introduction

MAME supports plugins that can provide additional functionality. Plugins have been written to communicate with external programs, play games automatically, display internal game structures like hitboxes, provide alternate user interfaces, and automatically test emulation. See Lua Scripting Interface for more information about MAME’s Lua API.

Using plugins

To enable plugins, you need to turn on the plugins option, and make sure the pluginspath option includes the folder where your plugins are stored. You can set the plugins option in an INI file or on the command line. You can set the pluginspath option by selecting Configure Options from the system selection menu, then selecting Configure Directories, and then selecting Plugins (you can also set it in an INI file or on the command line).

Many plugins need to store settings and/or data. The homepath option sets the folder where plugins should save data (defaults to the working directory). You can change this by selecting Configure Options from the system selection menu, then selecting Configure Directories, and then selecting Plugin Data.

To turn individual plugins on or off, first make sure plugins are enabled, then select Configure Options from the system selection menu, and then select Plugins. You will need to completely exit MAME and start it again for changes to the enabled plugins to take effect. You can also use the plugin option on the command line, or change the settings in the plugin.ini file.

If an enabled plugin needs additional configuration, or if it needs to show information, a Plugin Options item will appear in the main menu (accessed by pressing Tab during emulation by default).

Included plugins

MAME includes several plugins providing useful functionality, and serving as sample code that you can use as a starting point when writing your own plugins.

Autofire Plugin
Console Plugin
Data Plugin
Discord Presence Plugin
Dummy Test Plugin
GDB Stub Plugin
Hiscore Support Plugin
Input Macro Plugin
Layout Plugin
Timecode Recorder Plugin
Game Play Timer Plugin